Guide to the Robert S. Rankin Papers, 1957-1973
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Robert S. Rankin papers 1957-1973
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Rankin, Robert S. (Robert Stanley), 1899-1976
67.6 Linear Feet 17,000 Items
Robert S. Rankin was a professor of Political Science at Duke University and member of the United States Commission on Civil Rights.
Collection documents Rankin's work on the U.S. Civil Rights Commission, 1960-1973 and consists of agendas and minutes for the monthly meetings of the commission, 1959-1973, and material on special meetings; memoranda, correspondence, statements, and news clippings dealing with the operational aspects of the commission; background studies; transcripts of proceedings; news clippings from fact finding investigations, 1960-1973; statements of commissioners; and transcripts of testimony before congressional committees. The commission's areas of study included education, employment, political participation, housing and urban development, administration of justice, public accommodations, health and welfare, federal programs, minority groups, federal enforcement, and civil liberties and human rights.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
RESTRICTED: Collection has access restrictions.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Robert S. Rankin Papers, 1957-1973 were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift between 1990 and 2001.
Biographical Note
Robert S. Rankin was a professor of Political Science at Duke University and member of the United States Commission on Civil Rights.
Collection Overview
Collection documents Rankin's work on the U.S. Civil Rights Commission, 1960-1973 and consists of agendas and minutes for the monthly meetings of the commission, 1959-1973, and material on special meetings; memoranda, correspondence, statements, and news clippings dealing with the operational aspects of the commission; background studies; transcripts of proceedings; news clippings from fact finding investigations, 1960-1973; statements of commissioners; and transcripts of testimony before congressional committees. The commission's areas of study included education, employment, political participation, housing and urban development, administration of justice, public accommodations, health and welfare, federal programs, minority groups, federal enforcement, and civil liberties and human rights.
An addition (2001-0047) contains 27 loose black-and-white prints and 2 binders containing 89 black-and-white prints, as well as 35 items of correspondence (1963-1977) relating to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights. Includes group pictures of the commissioners and other political figures (1960-1969) and photographs from the National Conference on Equal Opportunity in Federally Assisted Programs (1965) and an Open Hearing in Jackson, Mississippi (1965). The open hearing includes a list of witnesses. Those represented in the photographs include Burke Marshall, Hubert H. Humphrey, Robert F. Kennedy, Sheriff Jack Purvis, Charles Evers, Aaron Henry, Spottswood Robinson, and Roy Wilkins.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Civil rights -- United States
College teachers -- Political activity
Duke University -- Faculty
United States -- Social conditions -- 1960-1980
United States Commission on Civil Rights
Contents of Collection
- United States Commission on Civil Right: Files, 1958-1976, (159 boxes)
  [RESTRICTED: Some files have access restrictions]
  - Guide to files (Box 1)
    [Access restricted]
  - Meetings 1958-1962 (Box 1)
  - Meetings 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Meetings 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - Meetings 1969 Jan. - 1970 Jan. (Box 4)
  - Meetings 1970 Feb. - 1971 June (Box 5)
  - Meetings 1971 Aug. - 1973 July (Box 6)
  - Meetings 1973 Sep. - 1973 Dec. (Box 7)
  - Meetings 1974 Jan. - 1974 March (Box 8)
  - Meetings 1974 April - 1974 June (Box 9)
  - Meetings 1974 Aug. - 1974 Sep. (Box 10)
  - Meetings 1974 Oct. - 1974 Nov. (Box 11)
  - Meetings 1974 Dec. (Box 12)
  - Meetings 1975 Jan. - 1975 March (Box 13)
  - Meetings 1975 April - 1975 May (Box 14)
  - Meetings 1975 June (Box 15)
  - Meetings 1975 July-1975 Sep. (Box 16)
  - Meetings 1975 Oct. - 1975 Dec. (Box 17)
  - Meetings 1976 Jan.-1976 Feb. (Box 18)
  - Meetings 1976 March - 1976 April (Box 19)
  - Meetings 1976 May - 1976 June (Box 20)
  - Commission Operations: rules, organization, jurisdiction, independence, extension (Box 21)
  - Commission Operations: commission, commissioners, communications, personnel reports (Box 22)
  - Commission Operations: employment practices, personnel statements, appointments/resignations, directories (Box 23)
  - Commission Operations: liaison activities, publications, catalogues, political parties, library acquisitions (Box 24)
  - Commission Operations: programs and projects, status of commission, recommendations 1959-1975 (Box 25)
  - Budget and appropriations FI 1960-FI 1972 (Box 26)
  - Commission Operations: finances (budget/appropriations, FY 1973-1974), misc. vitae (Box 27)
  - Commission Operations: finances (booklets, fiscal year 1970-FY 1974) (Box 28)
  - Commission Operations: finances (booklets, fiscal year 1975-FY 1977), budget analysis, fiscal year 1972-FY 1975 (Box 29)
  - Budget and appropriations FI 1960-FI 1972 (Box 30)
  - Commission Operations: activity reports: 1966 April - 1969 Dec. (Box 31)
  - Commission Operations: activity reports: 1970 - 1973 Jan. (Box 32)
  - Commission Operations: activity reports: 1963 July - 1972 April (Box 33)
  - Commission Operations: calendars, offices, monitoring system, misc., scholar in residence program (Box 34)
  - State advisory committees: rules and regulations, administrative operations, functions, SAC Report: 1975, directories (Box 35)
  - State advisory committees: directories: 1971-1972 (Box 36)
  - Advisory committees: publications, meetings, LittleJohn Report, personnel, activity reports, 1960-1962 (Box 37)
  - State advisory committees: personnel reports, 1963-1973 (Box 38)
  - SAC: personnel reports, rechartering, Alabama-Louisiana (Box 39)
  - personnel reports, rechartering, Maine-New York (Box 40)
  - personnel reports, rechartering, North Carolina-Wyoming (Box 41)
  - SAC: Alabama-Florida (Box 42)
  - SAC: Georgia-Michigan (Box 43)
  - SAC: Minnesota-New York (Box 44)
  - SAC: North Carolina-Pennsylvania (Box 45)
  - SAC: RI-Wyoming (Box 46)
  - Conferences: Notre Dame conference on Civil Rights, 1960, Conference on Education 1960, Conference on Administration of Justice, 1960 (Box 47)
  - Conferences: 4th Annual Conference on Education 1962, Opportunity on Federal Programs 1965, Regional Conferences 1965, White House Conference on Civil Rights (Box 48)
  - Conferences: White House Conference "To Fulfill These Rights" 1966, National on Race and Education parts 1 and 2 1967 (Box 49)
  - Conferences: Race and Education 1967, White House Conference on Children 1970, Anti-Racism Techniques 1970, Leadership Conference 1970, National Civil Rights Conference 1973 (Box 50)
  - Hearings: New Orleans-voting 1960 (Box 51)
  - Hearings: Detroit 1960, Baltimore 1961, Phoenix 1962 (Box 52)
  - Hearings: Washington DC, Memphis, Newark, Jackson (Box 53)
  - Hearings: Indianapolis 1963, Jackson 1965 (Box 54)
  - Hearings: Jackson 1965, Rochester 1966, Syracuse 1966 (Box 55)
  - Hearings: Cleveland: education, employment, health, housing, law enforcement, welfare 1966 (Box 56)
  - Hearings: Boston: education and racial isolation 1966, San Francisco: education, employment, housing 1967 (Box 57)
  - Hearings: San Francisco 1967, Montgomery 1968 (Box 58)
  - Hearings: Montgomery 1968, San Antonio: Mexican Americans 1968 (Box 59)
  - Hearings: Orangeburg, SC: Law Enforcement 1968, San Diego: Education 1969, St. Louis: employment and housing 1970, Baltimore: suburban development 1970 (Box 60)
  - Hearings: St. Louis: employment and housing 1970 (Box 61)
  - Hearings: LA: Mexican Americans 1970, Washington: racial polarization 1971, New York: Puerto Ricans 1972 (Box 62)
  - Hearings: Cairo, IL 1972: economic development, education, employment, health, housing, law enforcement (Box 63)
  - Hearings: Cairo, IL 1972, Albuquerque: American Indians 1972, Widow Rock, AZ: American Indians 1973 (Box 64)
  - Hearings: Window Rock, AZ 1973 (Box 65)
  - Hearings: Chicago: Women's rights 1974 (Box 66)
  - Hearings: Boston: school desegregation 1975, briefing session, official memoranda and correspondence (Box 67)
  - Hearings: Boston: school desegregation 1975, interviews, staff report draft, interim progress report, clippings (Box 68)
  - Hearings: Denver: school desegregation 1976 (Box 69)
  - Hearings: Tampa: school desegregation 1976 (Box 70)
  - Hearings: Tampa: school desegregation 1976 (Box 71)
  - Short report 1959, civil rights appraisal, civil rights in America, interim reports 1963 (Box 72)
  - Civil rights progress report 1971, racial and ethnic data report 1972 (Box 73)
  - Publications 1960-1976 (Box 74)
  - Memoranda and correspondence: regional reports 1963-1976 (Box 75)
  - Statements and addresses 1959-1972, clippings (Box 76)
  - Civil rights project 1958-1959: US Report, State reports: AL-MO (Box 77)
  - Civil rights project 1958-1959, Montana-Wyoming (Box 78)
  - Congressional legislation 1958-1967, 1971 (Box 79)
  - Hearings Before the US Congressional Committees on the Judiciary 1957 Feb-1959 May (Box 80)
  - Hearings Before the US Congressional Committees on the Judiciary 1959 July-1963 May (Box 81)
  - Education: USCCR Report 1959, parts 1-5 (Box 82)
  - Education (reports): 1959 Report, Public Higher Education 1960 (Box 83)
  - Education (reports): Three Judge District Courts and Desegregation of Public Colleges 1961, USCCR Annual Report (Box 84)
  - Education: Equal protection of laws in public schools 1962- Northwest cities, Southern States (Box 85)
  - Education: Public education 1963, segregation status of Southern Schools, 1964 (Box 86)
  - Education: public education 1960 (Box 87)
  - Education: Southern School Desegregation, survey of school desegregation, racial isolation in the public schools, 1966 (Box 88)
  - Education: racial isolation in the public school 1967 (Box 89)
  - Education (reports): southern school desegregation 1966-1967, education of disadvantaged children 1968, Mexican American study, Federal enforcement of school desegregation (Box 90)
  - Education (reports): school desegregation: Sacramento, Charlottesville, Providence, progress and problems in school desegregation (Box 91)
  - Education: what students perceive 1970, public attitudes regarding busing 1972, overcoming desegregation problems 1972 (Box 92)
  - Education: bilingual and bi-cultural education 1975 (Box 93)
  - Education: "Desegregating the Boston Public Schools: A Crisis in Civic Responsibility" 1975 Aug. (Box 94)
  - Education: Desegregation in Prince George's County 1976, official memoranda and correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 95)
  - Education: official memoranda and correspondence 1960-1962 (Box 96)
  - Education: Equal Educational Opportunities Act 1972-1974 (Box 97)
  - Official memoranda and correspondence 1974, congressional testimony 1960-1972, clippings 1959-1966 (Box 98)
  - Education: clippings 1967-1973 (Box 99)
  - Education: statements and addresses 1961-1973, court opinions 1962-1973 (Box 100)
  - Education: Progress reports 1960-1961, staff study 1962, publications 1957-1973, misc. (Box 101)
  - Education: Misc. reports and studies (Box 102)
  - Education: "Rand Study": school desegregation volumes 1-3, 1974 May (Box 103)
  - Education: "Rand Study": school desegregation volumes 1-3, 1974 Sep. (Box 104)
  - Education: "Rand Study" school desegregation, official memoranda and correspondence 1973-1975 (Box 105)
  - Education: Seidenberg Report 1960, USCCR Annual Report 1961 (Box 106)
  - Employment Reports: Job, Training, and the Negro, 1963; The Disadvantaged Poor 1966; State and local study 1968 (Box 107)
  - Employment (reports): jobs and civil rights, equal employment opportunity programs 1969 (Box 108)
  - Employment: official memoranda and correspondence 1960-1963, statements and testimonies, publications, clippings (Box 109)
  - Employment reports: printed material 1975, clippings, court opinions (Box 110)
  - Political participation reports (Box 111)
  - Political participation reports: 1961 reports: voting, blackbelt (Box 112)
  - Political participation reports: voting rights act of 1965, voting in MI 1965, participation 1968 (Box 113)
  - Political participation: Blackbelt survey 1960, official memoranda and correspondence 1960-1974 (Box 114)
  - Political participation reports: official memoranda and correspondence 1975-1976: The Voting Rights Act - Ten Years After (Box 115)
  - Political participation: legislation, congressional testimony, court opinions, clippings (Box 116)
  - Housing reports: USCCR reports 1959-1961 (Box 117)
  - Housing reports: Second Commission Draft 1959 (Box 118)
  - Housing reports: Washington DC 1962, family housing 1963, civil rights USA/housing 1963 (Box 119)
  - Housing: Defense Department Housing Report 1968, HEW Title 6 survey, USCCR report, official memoranda and correspondence 1959-1973 (Box 120)
  - Housing: progress reports 1960-1961, statements 1962-1973, congressional testimony 1968-1971, clippings (Box 121)
  - Urban development (reports): civil rights USA/urban areas 1963, A Time to Listen, A Time to Act 1967, staff reports 1970, suburban access 1971 (Box 122)
  - Urban development: suburban access report, New York City report 1972, suburbia report 1973, official memoranda and correspondence 1960-1973 (Box 123)
  - Urban development: publications, clippings (Box 124)
  - Administration of Justice (reports): equal justice under law 1959, USCCR report 1961 (Box 125)
  - Administration of Justice (reports): civil rights USA/justice 1961-1963, law enforcement in the South 1965 (Box 126)
  - Administration of Justice: law enforcement in the South report 1965 (Box 127)
  - Administration of Justice: statements and testimony, Time vs. Pape 1971, publications, UN Report 1962, clippings, Emmett Till case 1955 (Box 128)
  - Administration of Justice: public accommodations report 1962; health and welfare: health facilities report 1963, Tuskegee study 1973, family assistance plan, Texas food programs (Box 129)
  - Federal programs: Appraisal of civil rights act Title 6 1966, Headstart Program proposal 1966, USCCR Report 1970, official memoranda and correspondence 1961-1973 (Box 130)
  - Minority groups: general, racism: reports, office memoranda, publications (Box 131)
  - Minority groups: women: official memoranda, equal rights amendments, reproductive freedom 1974-1975 (Box 132)
  - Minority groups: women: Women's Rights hearings 1974, clippings, publications (Box 133)
  - Federal programs: publications, revenue sharing, intergovernmentalism, state's rights, federal advisory committee act, 1972 (Box 134)
  - Federal programs: revenue sharing (Box 135)
  - American Indians: Albuquerque hearing report, Phoenix hearing report, education report 1972, Southwest Indian report 1973, Navajo 1975 (Box 136)
  - American Indians: civil rights survey 1960, Indian civil rights handbook 1971, staff reports, 1972-1973, rights of American Indians to food programs, 1972 (Box 137)
  - American Indians: official memoranda and correspondence 1969-1974, statements and addresses, clippings, Navajo hearing interviews and briefing 1973 (Box 138)
  - Asian Americans and Puerto Ricans reports (Box 139)
  - Minority groups (Box 140)
  - Blacks: Official memoranda and correspondence 1958-1972, statements and addresses, publications, clippings, Jewish relations, Black Panthers (Box 141)
  - Mexican Americans reports: Spanish speaking peoples 1964, Mexican Americans of the Southwest 1965, administration of justice in the Southwest 1969 (Box 142)
  - Mexican Americans reports: education study 1970-1972, political participation in CA 1971, "Stranger in One's Land" 1970 (Box 143)
  - Mexican Americans reports: education study 1973 (Box 144)
  - Mexican Americans: education study report, education neglect report 1973, official memoranda and correspondence 1964-1973, statements, publications, clippings (Box 145)
  - Federal enforcement reports: civil rights act 1964, department of interior survey 1968, mechanism for implementing Title 6 1968-1969, USCCR Report 1970 (Box 146)
  - Federal enforcement reports: federal civil rights enforcement effort 1971, federal agency responses to USCCR questionnaire 1971 (Box 147)
  - Federal enforcement reports: federal agency responses to USCCR questionnaire 1971, contract compliance 1972, restricted (Box 148)
  - Federal enforcement reports: USCCR Report 1973 (Box 149)
  - Federal enforcement reports: USCCR Report 1974: v. 1: To Regulate in the Public Interest v. 2 To Provide for Fair Housing (Box 150)
  - Federal enforcement reports: USCCR Report 1974: v. 3: To Ensure Equal Education Opportunity, v. 4: To Provide Fiscal Assistance (Box 151)
  - Federal enforcement reports: USCCR Report 1974: v. 5: To Eliminate Employment Discrimination, Official memoranda and correspondence 1975 (Box 152)
  - Federal enforcement reports: USCCR Report 1974: v. 6: To Extend Federal Financial Assistance, official memoranda and correspondence 1975-1976 (Box 153)
  - Federal enforcement reports: USCCR Report 1974: v. 7 To Preserve, Protect, and Defend the Constitution (Box 154)
  - Twenty Years After Brown: Civil Rights and Race Relations in America 1974, The Shadow of the Past (Box 155)
  - Twenty Years After Brown: Equality of Educational Opportunity, 1974, Equality of Economic Opportunity 1975, Equal Opportunity Housing 1975 (Box 156)
  - Federal Enforcement: Official memoranda and correspondence 1959-1973, statements and addresses, publications, clippings 1964-1973 (Box 157)
  - Civil Liberties: official memoranda and correspondence, testimony, publications; human rights: official memoranda, publications (Box 158)
  - Misc. (Box 159)
- Other Files, 1932-1976, (10 boxes)
  - Durham City County Charter Commission: Consolidation Study 1932, 1957, 1959-1960, clippings 1971-1974 (Box 160)
  - Durham Chamber of Commerce: "Governments: A Report on City and County" 1970, Institute of Government 1969, NC Local Government Study Commission, UNC Board Study Commission (Box 161)
  - Correspondence 1956-1960 (Box 162)
  - Correspondence 1961-1963 (Box 163)
  - Correspondence 1964-1965 (Box 164)
  - Correspondence 1966 (Box 165)
  - Correspondence 1967 (Box 166)
  - Correspondence 1968 (Box 167)
  - Correspondence 1969-1970 (Box 168)
  - Correspondence 1971-1976 (Box 169)
- Accession (2001-0047), 1960-1977, (1 box)
  Addition includes 27 loose black-and-white prints and 2 binders containing 89 black-and-white prints, as well as 35 items of correspondence (1963-1977) relating to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights. Includes group pictures of the commissioners and other political figures (1960-1969) and photographs from the National Conference on Equal Opportunity in Federally Assisted Programs (1965) and an Open Hearing in Jackson, Mississippi (1965). The open hearing includes a list of witnesses. Those represented in the photographs include Burke Marshall, Hubert H. Humphrey, Robert F. Kennedy, Sheriff Jack Purvis, Charles Evers, Aaron Henry, Spottswood Robinson, and Roy Wilkins.
  - Accession (2001-0047) (Box 1)